<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Girls | Economy of Effort]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.economyofeffort.com/categories/girls/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.economyofeffort.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-07-20T16:55:07-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.economyofeffort.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Brendon Rapp]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[An Institution of Learning]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.economyofeffort.com/2008/05/29/an-institution-of-learning/"/>
    <updated>2008-05-29T08:36:38-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.economyofeffort.com/2008/05/29/an-institution-of-learning</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.economyofeffort.com/wp-content/uploads/2008/05/monache1.jpg"><img src="http://www.economyofeffort.com/wp-content/uploads/2008/05/monache1.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>This is my old high school. I can&rsquo;t believe someone bothered with a class gift. Clearly someone ruined the student apathy my class worked hard to build.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.economyofeffort.com/wp-content/uploads/2008/05/monache2.jpg"><img src="http://www.economyofeffort.com/wp-content/uploads/2008/05/monache2.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>That&rsquo;s Sam&rsquo;s ear.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Propelled into Dreamland]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.economyofeffort.com/2006/07/15/propelled-into-dreamland/"/>
    <updated>2006-07-15T03:03:46-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.economyofeffort.com/2006/07/15/propelled-into-dreamland</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://www.economyofeffort.com/media/images/loughlin.jpg" alt="" />What happens when your late night TV viewing consists of Full House and a PBS show on string theory?</p>

<p><img src="http://www.economyofeffort.com/media/images/morgan-webb.jpg" alt="" />You get a dream about Full House characters getting stuck in an alternate reality (which happens to be evil) using their wits and powers of persuasion to avoid 24 hour lockdown by the evil Full House character counterparts. They then prepare a daring last-second escape and destruction of the evil world (which involved tossing some kind of powder from the non-evil world into a shallow pool of water, and submerging themselves in the water), and pull it off with the aid of a monkey from the evil world that wasn&rsquo;t evil (because monkeys are always good).</p>

<p>This is what my head concocts when left to its own devices.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s not so bad, though. The night before last, the dream involved me and a half-naked Morgan Webb hanging in a hotel. If I can figure out the late-night TV combination that creates that, I&rsquo;ll patent it.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Games and my 25-Year Old Girlfriend Fiancee, Part II]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.economyofeffort.com/2006/06/08/games-and-my-25-year-old-girlfriend-fiancee-part-ii/"/>
    <updated>2006-06-08T14:47:01-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.economyofeffort.com/2006/06/08/games-and-my-25-year-old-girlfriend-fiancee-part-ii</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://static.flickr.com/53/163462725_276e520716_o.jpg" alt="" /> When it comes to games, Stacey has two modes &ndash; indifferent and obsessed. She either couldn&rsquo;t care less about a game, or (for those lucky few rare games) she becomes so enamored by them that she MUST have them immediately, and plays them for hours non-stop. This Sunday, as mentioned in the last post, she is getting a Nintendo DS Lite, and I couldn&rsquo;t be more proud. In the meantime, though, she discovered a new game to be obsessed with while fiddling around with the GameCube kiosks at GameStop stores. That game is Chibi-Robo, which (from all I&rsquo;ve seen of it) involves walking around as a miniature robot and collecting trash and mopping up muddy paw prints. Stacey definitely likes the &ldquo;go around and do things&rdquo; genre of games, and her DS Lite will glow late into the evenings playing Animal Crossing in a few days, no doubt.</p>

<p>She&rsquo;s also discovered Zuma, a puzzle game on Xbox Live Arcade. And that&rsquo;s a pretty fresh and unique puzzle game. Anyone with a 360 should give the demo a shot.</p>

<p>And, best of all, she&rsquo;s playing Beyond Good and Evil. That&rsquo;s my girl.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Dumb Stuff]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.economyofeffort.com/2005/12/01/dumb-stuff/"/>
    <updated>2005-12-01T12:49:19-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.economyofeffort.com/2005/12/01/dumb-stuff</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I don&rsquo;t care for celebrity &ldquo;news&rdquo; much, but it&rsquo;s hard to pass on this one: <a href="http://www.contactmusic.com/new/xmlfeed.nsf/mndwebpages/hiltons%20santa%20claus%20heartbreak">Paris Hilton believed in Santa Claus until she was 17.</a> She must&rsquo;ve at least figured it out by herself by then, right? Nope. Quote the trashy ho, &ldquo;a mean person told me it wasn&rsquo;t true.&rdquo;</p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s a mildly funny clip from Stacey&rsquo;s favorite TV show, Boy Meets World: <a href="http://www.economyofeffort.com/media/video/BMW_showedhim.avi">Corey wants to see more of Topanga (6MB video)</a>. What guy wouldn&rsquo;t want to see that side of Danielle Fishel? Funny how episodes like this don&rsquo;t seem to get shown on Disney Channel. Oh well. Here she is <a href="http://www.famous-people-search.com/danielle_fishel/danielle_fishel_pictures/danielle_fishel_001.jpg">decked out football style</a>. A Rashaan Salaam jersey never looked so good.</p>

<p>I don&rsquo;t read or watch anything Harry Potter. I think I&rsquo;ve seen <a href="http://bilder.filmstarts.de/verzeichnis/film/filme/h/harry.potter.4/HarryPotterIV-08.jpg">this blonde French girl</a> (the one on the left, not Gandalf!)  in previews for the next movie or something though. Well, when people looked at her past work, they found she had been <a href="http://wwtdd.com/index.php?type=one&amp;i=325">acting in the buff in some French film</a>. I wonder if that&rsquo;s what got her noticed by the Potter heads?</p>

<p>I recently discovered that <a href="http://progreviews.com/reviews/display.php?rev=be-agw">Brian Eno&rsquo;s &ldquo;Another Green World&rdquo;</a> is a good album.</p>

<p>NPR&rsquo;s <a href="http://www.npr.org/programs/asc/">All Songs Considered</a> podcast is good too. Covers some music that I don&rsquo;t normally keep that close of an eye on. Though recent episodes have featured stuff from Adrian Belew, Kasabian, and Gentle Giant, as well as the <a href="http://www.bluenote.com/detail.asp?SelectionID=10459">lost Coltrane/Monk recording</a> that was discovered at the Library of Congress only this year.</p>

<p>Have you updated to Firefox 1.5? If not, <a href="http://www.mozilla.org/">get on with it already</a>.</p>

<p>So the Sharks traded for Joe Thornton. Big deal. It doesn&rsquo;t fix <a href="http://www.basketballdraft.com/hockey/2002/playoffs/news/2002/05/13/avs_sharks_ap/lg_nabokov_ap-01.jpg">their real problem</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Manson, Shirley]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.economyofeffort.com/2005/07/23/manson-shirley/"/>
    <updated>2005-07-23T17:45:48-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.economyofeffort.com/2005/07/23/manson-shirley</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>What sort of twisted reality do we live in where Shirley Manson is almost 40 years old?</p>

<p><img src="http://img.photobucket.com/albums/v654/legion_sb/012.jpg" alt="Shirley Manson grabbing her wonderous breasts" />
<img src="http://img.photobucket.com/albums/v654/legion_sb/021.jpg" alt="Manson and her hot red hair" /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
