<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Games | Economy of Effort]]></title>
  <link href="http://brendonrapp.github.io/categories/games/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://brendonrapp.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-07-20T02:04:46-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://brendonrapp.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Brendon Rapp]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Battlefield 3: Get out of my way!]]></title>
    <link href="http://brendonrapp.github.io/2011/11/03/battlefield-3-get-out-of-my-way/"/>
    <updated>2011-11-03T05:02:29-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://brendonrapp.github.io/2011/11/03/battlefield-3-get-out-of-my-way</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Dear Battlefield 3,</p>

<p><img src="http://www.economyofeffort.com/wp-content/uploads/2011/11/bf3.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p><strong>Yes, I know I&rsquo;m in a Conquest checkpoint&rsquo;s capture radius!</strong> The little map in the corner that&rsquo;s got a big box next to me kind of gave that fact away.</p>

<p>Now will you please <strong>get the mother-fudge out of the way?</strong> I am trying to look at things where you&rsquo;ve got your big obnoxious indicator.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[5 Things I Think I Think about... Resident Evil 4]]></title>
    <link href="http://brendonrapp.github.io/2009/04/21/5-things-i-think-i-think-about-resident-evil-4/"/>
    <updated>2009-04-21T06:58:23-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://brendonrapp.github.io/2009/04/21/5-things-i-think-i-think-about-resident-evil-4</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>5 Things I Think I Think about&hellip;</p>

<p><img src="http://www.economyofeffort.com/wp-content/uploads/2009/04/re4.jpg" alt="re4" /></p>

<p><strong>1. I think the Wii version is the only one I can stand playing.</strong> This run-through of RE4 was the third time I tried to play the game. The first two false-starts were on the GameCube and the PC. I found the one-stick control style on the GameCube to be abhorant. The PC version looked <em>beautiful</em>, like a completely different game compared to the Cube and Wii versions (just from the high resolution support, really). But even with a 360 gamepad, the game was insistant on mapping movement and aiming to the left stick.</p>

<p>By moving the aiming system to the Wiimote and putting movement on the nunchuk, the Wii version is the only one that uses a true two-sets-of-axes system &ndash; you know, the control approach that is the reason every gamepad comes with two analog sticks now. You still can&rsquo;t move and shoot at the same time, but the player&rsquo;s left thumb is no longer performing this awkward double-duty while the right thumb twiddles&hellip; itself.</p>

<p>The Wiimote aiming scheme isn&rsquo;t a 1:1 mapped &ldquo;pointer&rdquo; like one might intuitively expect. Rather, the Wiimote acts, as one Gamers With Jobs poster describes it, like a giant right analog stick. It&rsquo;s nice and responsive, and allows for pretty good fine aiming control.</p>

<p>There were some baffling control issues from time to time, though. When aiming through the rifle scope, the Wiimote no longer controls aiming, but rather the nunchuk stick does! This is jarring, of course, because the rest of the game uses the Wiimote for aiming. But what is worse is that the nunchuk stick is <em>very</em> sensitive, in part (I imagine) because it&rsquo;s only used for movement and camera control throughout the rest of the game. Aiming through the scope with the hyper-sensitive nunchuk stick is a bitch and a half. I understand that the rifle scope is a &ldquo;fixed view&rdquo; rather than a floating aim cursor like non-scoped weapons. But there still ought to be an option to aim with the Wiimote, which offers the fine movement control that the sensitive nunchuk stick lacks.</p>

<p>Oh, and to add one little wrinkle: I&rsquo;m an inverted control sort of person. Not just thumbsticks, either, but mice too. Everything. Aiming with the Wiimote is pretty natural, but at first I found myself having a hard time dealing with the nunchuk&rsquo;s stick for &ldquo;looking&rdquo; around while aiming. Pushing &ldquo;up&rdquo; to look down is natural for me, but at the same time it felt at odds with how my right hand moved to go &ldquo;up&rdquo;. Trying to switch the nunchuk&rsquo;s stick back to Normal, however, was disasterous. Eventually, my brain was able to deal with the slight disconnect, and my inverted thumbstick and pointed Wiimote worked in harmony.</p>

<p><img src="http://www.economyofeffort.com/wp-content/uploads/2009/04/resident_evil_4__wii_edition.jpg" alt="resident_evil_4__wii_edition" /></p>

<p><strong>2. I think the Wiimote-aimed exploding headshot is one of the most satisfying &ldquo;kills&rdquo; in any game I&rsquo;ve played recently.</strong> I could very easily spend these 5 Things just rattling off complaints about the game. In fact, that&rsquo;s sort of what my first draft of this looked like. So I took a step back and tried to put my finger on why I enjoyed the 16 hours I sunk into this game. I&rsquo;ve been a fan of previous Resident Evil games, but this one was a very different experience. The one thing that I could point to with zero hesitation was the satisfaction behind every well-placed shot. Being rid of the awkward, uncomfortable feeling of trying to aim with my left thumb (my &ldquo;non-aiming&rdquo; thumb, you could say) helped with this feeling, I&rsquo;m sure.</p>

<p><strong>3. I think the visuals in this port deserved some attention that they didn&rsquo;t receive.</strong> It probably looks just fine on an SDTV, but blown up on my 47" 1080p panel, even with the Wii component cables, RE4 on the Wii was a jagged, muddy mess. This doesn&rsquo;t <em>truly</em> come across in screenshots, which don&rsquo;t look particularly bad. But in action, the game&rsquo;s great detail was partially lost in the upconversion process.</p>

<p>I understand that the game also makes use of the Wii&rsquo;s &ldquo;deflicker&rdquo; filter, which softens and blurs the image. Some Wii games, like Super Smash Bros. Brawl, make this filter a user-selectable option. RE4, however, has no such option. The blurred image doesn&rsquo;t do enough to deal with the heavy aliasing. Really, it just blurs away any edge definition, and makes it difficult for things to stand out from the background.</p>

<p>At the very least, I wish the Wii supported higher output resolutions.</p>

<p><img src="http://www.economyofeffort.com/wp-content/uploads/2009/04/re4_ss01.jpg" alt="re4_ss01" /></p>

<p><strong>4. I think the game really tried to piss me off.</strong><strong> </strong>None of the sections in this game were unduly difficult. A couple required repeating, but nothing brought progress to a halt or raised frustration levels from excessive challenge. The game was quite adept, though, at doing small things to piss me off.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m OK with the tank-like movement in RE games. I&rsquo;m not OK with areas that have enemies drop from above to land <strong>right next</strong> to me, irritatingly poking at the weaknesses of the RE combat style. (This one wasn&rsquo;t <em>too</em> bad on the Wii, where I could reach the edges of the screen with the crosshair even before holding the button to go into &ldquo;aim&rdquo; mode, but I can&rsquo;t imagine how much I would have howled at these situtations if I had to deal with the GameCube aiming.)</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m not OK with enemy and boss types that involve running around with the enemy <em>off the screen</em> the majority of the time. You didn&rsquo;t make the RE4 camera or combat system for these. Don&rsquo;t do them. The Garridors (the blind claw guys) and the Gigantes were just <em>awful</em>. Some of the worst moments of the game.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m not OK with the maddening inconsistency with how enemies react to taking bullets to the face. Some enemies, like the big dudes with axes, might normally stumble after taking a bullet or two to the dome. But then, randomly, they would decide that they could shrug off a half-dozen hits to the face on their way to closing the gap and slashing you with a devastating axe chop. Look, is a bullet to the face going to deter this guy or not? Don&rsquo;t making a certain approach to an enemy a winning tactic 90% of the time, but then gash me for half my health the other 10% of the time.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m never, <em>ever, ever</em> OK with item boxes that contain a trap instead of an item &ndash; in this case, a snake. OK, if it&rsquo;s a DnD-style game, and detecting traps is part of the game world, fine. But if not, what&rsquo;s the point? You&rsquo;re not turning the box into a risk/reward scenario. The player <em>has</em> to hit up every single box. He/she is totally dependent on them for acquiring sufficient supplies to progress. All sticking a snake in there does is punish the player for a choice that he/she <em>has to make</em>. (And yes, I know killing the snake yields a healing item. It doesn&rsquo;t make the idea any less dumb.)</p>

<p><img src="http://www.economyofeffort.com/wp-content/uploads/2009/04/395158-image15_super.gif" alt="395158-image15_super" /></p>

<p><strong>5. I think I had my best gaming &ldquo;ticking bomb&rdquo; scenario ever.</strong> Near the end of the game, there&rsquo;s a boss fight (Krauser) that requires beating the boss and exiting the &ldquo;room&rdquo; before a 3-minute countdown timer hits zero. As I finished off Krauser and bolted for the exit, my time ran awfully low. When I got to the exit door, there was less than a second on the clock. But I had to stick 3 things into the door to reveal a door behind it that I could actually exit through.</p>

<p>I mashed the &ldquo;A&rdquo; button as fast as I could. The clock wouldn&rsquo;t count as the game &ldquo;placed&rdquo; the objects, but it would start back up again as soon as one was placed. I mashed faster. By the time the actual exit door was revealed and control returned back to me to register one last pound of the &ldquo;A&rdquo; button, the clock was down to 00:00.07 &ndash; seven hundredths of a second.</p>

<p>I don&rsquo;t know how punishing the game is when that clock reaches zero. Maybe there&rsquo;s a second or so of hesitation, or maybe being all the way by the door was &ldquo;clear enough&rdquo; of the blast. Or maybe it was indeed instant death at 00:00.00. I didn&rsquo;t intend on finding out. All I know is that when I saw Leon finally enter the door with seven hundredths of a second left, I thought to myself, &ldquo;<strong>oh damn!</strong>&rdquo;.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[5 Things: Far Cry]]></title>
    <link href="http://brendonrapp.github.io/2009/04/07/5-things-far-cry/"/>
    <updated>2009-04-07T12:46:27-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://brendonrapp.github.io/2009/04/07/5-things-far-cry</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In honor of <a href="http://sportsillustrated.cnn.com/writers/peter_king/archive/">Peter King</a>&rsquo;s &ldquo;5 Things I Think I Think&rdquo; musing on the NFL, I present my own &ldquo;five things&rdquo; on games I have recently played.</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s kick things off with 5 Things I Think I Think about&hellip;</p>

<p><img src="http://www.techpowerup.com/reviews/EVGA/GeForce_8800_GS/images/farcry.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p><strong>1. I think I&rsquo;m in love with the &ldquo;sandbox&rdquo; approach to shooter battles.</strong> The game Far Cry was when I was funneled through hallways and tunnels is probably a game I would have played and enjoyed, even if at a C+, B- level or so. The game Far Cry was when I was allowed to sneak through brush, survey hostiles in the distance, plan a course of action, and execute it, is a game I <em>loved</em>.</p>

<p>For a game that wasn&rsquo;t strictly a stealth action title, I was surprised at how reasonable and &ldquo;fair&rdquo; the enemy&rsquo;s ability to detect the player was. There were very, very few instances of &ldquo;how the heck did he &lsquo;see&rsquo; me?&rdquo;. I always felt comfortable that, if there was enough brush in front of me to block them from my view, I would in turn be blocked from their view.</p>

<p>I really enjoyed the freedom of being able to approach situations from many different angles. I often eschewed taking vehicles and running through what was clearly a planned &ldquo;vehicle&rdquo; sequence, opting instead to creep through the vegetation. It was extremely satisfying to be able to exercise a little <em>creativity</em> in playing the game. So many games really force you to flip the &ldquo;off&rdquo; switch in your brain and just follow in-game cues. How many times have you been playing a game and asked yourself, &ldquo;what am I <em>supposed</em> to do?&rdquo;, instead of, &ldquo;how <em>can</em> I approach this?&rdquo;. As gamers, we&rsquo;ve become conditioned to try and seek the designed course of action. Years and years of &ldquo;locked&rdquo; doors and invisible walls have taught us to turn off the brain and follow the cues.</p>

<p>Given this newfound love for &ldquo;sandbox&rdquo; FPS battles, it seems like kismet that the FPS games at the top of my &ldquo;to-play&rdquo; list are the following: Crysis, Crysis: Warhead, S.T.A.L.K.E.R., S.T.A.L.K.E.R.: Clear Sky, and Far Cry 2.</p>

<p><img src="http://www.economyofeffort.com/wp-content/uploads/2009/04/trigen.jpg" alt="trigen" /></p>

<p><strong>2. I think the mutant menace was extremely overstated.</strong> I didn&rsquo;t play Far Cry back in 2004-05 (save for the demo), but like any forum-dwelling gamer, I&rsquo;m well aware of its reputation: &ldquo;a great game, until those damn <em>mutants</em> showed up&rdquo;. So when the mutants &ndash; Trigens &ndash; showed up in level 5 (of 20), I thought the jig might be up. I&rsquo;ve been disciplining myself to pull the plug on games before they outlive their ability to entertain me, as it&rsquo;s my nature to simply want to <em>finish</em> them anyway. So, from mission 5 onward, we were on orange alert. And a few early encounters almost led to premature deletion, as getting pounced by one of those bastards was essentially insta-death.</p>

<p>But just before it all fell apart, the tides turned. I got a semiautomatic combat shotgun, giving me a capable counter to the pouncing mutants in close encounters. Then the &ldquo;CryVision&rdquo; night vision/thermal goggles were acquired, allowing me to hunt <em>them</em> in the outdoor areas. The mutants didn&rsquo;t dominate the rest of the game, as new enemies are often so prone to do &ndash; just when a mutant-heavy sequence would become tiresome, the game would swing back to encounters against theÂ  reasonably clever human AI enemies. And most important, the tunneled indoor areas always gave way to more expansive outdoor segments, returning the game to its bread and butter.</p>

<p>I would have preferred the game sans-mutants, which makes Far Cry 2 appealing, even if it&rsquo;s quite a different game. But the mutants failed to live up to their game-destroying reputation.</p>

<p><strong>3. I think I like ridiculous, juvenile &ldquo;sexual content&rdquo; a little too much.</strong> Please don&rsquo;t misunderstand me. I know a pathetic appeal to teenage nerd sexual fantasy when I see it. Like the obnoxious fawning from the demon girl in Dark Messiah of Might and Magic. But here&rsquo;s the thing&hellip;</p>

<p><img src="http://www.economyofeffort.com/wp-content/uploads/2009/04/farcryval01.jpg" alt="farcryval01" /></p>

<p><img src="http://www.economyofeffort.com/wp-content/uploads/2009/04/farcryval02.jpg" alt="farcryval02" /></p>

<p>&hellip; I just don&rsquo;t care.</p>

<p>I love it. Exaggerated virtual girls with over-the-top, oversexed attitudes and bodies to match&hellip; I love it all. No matter how fake, or how transparent the manipulation, I&rsquo;ll happily wallow in a sea of horny video game girls.</p>

<p><strong>4. I think waiting a few years to play the game was a good idea (also: Steam sales are the best).</strong> When the game was new, playing Far Cry at 1680x1050 with everything cranked to Very High would&rsquo;ve been a pipe dream. But with a nice midrange 8800 GT, that&rsquo;s exactly how I played the game, with a framerate that was permanently well above 60 fps. So, so butter smooth. I&rsquo;m a stickler for framerate. Nothing looks better than a game that runs silky smooth. I have Far Cry 2, and I can get good framerates with decent detail settings right now, but I&rsquo;m not firing up the game again until I get my new video card.</p>

<p>I bought Far Cry a couple of weekends ago, during Ubisoft&rsquo;s week of Steam sales. The weekend sale was a 4-pack: Beyond Good and Evil, Far Cry, IL-2 Sturmovik, and Dark Messiah of Might and Magic, all for $9.99. I already owned BG&amp;E and IL-2, but I figured that would just make Far Cry and Dark Messiah $5 each. I definitely got my $5 out of Far Cry.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve never regretted a Steam sale purchase, but I continue to regret purchases I <em>didn&rsquo;t</em> make (WHY did I not buy Vampire: Bloodlines for $10 back in October??)</p>

<p><img src="http://www.economyofeffort.com/wp-content/uploads/2009/04/farcry01.jpg" alt="farcry01" /></p>

<p><strong>5. I think I&rsquo;m glad I played the game on Medium difficulty.</strong> Far Cry was not a forgiving game. I think one of the reasons I was able to live with the mutant presence was because I wasn&rsquo;t playing on one of the advanced difficulty levels. Playing on harder difficulty levels is something that I&rsquo;m trying to discipline myself into doing. Too often, I cheat myself out of a rewarding challenge by just going with the default difficulty setting. Although it is fun to just blast through a game with no frustration, I have found that, like a badly coached sports team, I &ldquo;play down&rdquo; to the competition. I just cruise through on autopilot, and eventually find certain parts hard because I&rsquo;m not <em>really</em> trying.</p>

<p>Far Cry was not one of those games. I have no doubt that I could have prevailed on higher difficulty settings, but with a lot more frustration. Certain scenes clearly exist to beat the player senseless and force him/her to re-play the section many times in order to &ldquo;get it right&rdquo;. I was certainly annoyed by a couple of them, and I have no doubt that dealing with them on a hard difficulty would&rsquo;ve put a real dent in my enjoyment of the game. For this title at least, chickening out was the right way to go.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Blast Processing]]></title>
    <link href="http://brendonrapp.github.io/2008/03/12/blast-processing/"/>
    <updated>2008-03-12T04:18:36-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://brendonrapp.github.io/2008/03/12/blast-processing</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;ve kicked off the first of my new sites, a gaming/PC tech blog called <a href="http://www.blastprocessing.net">Blast Processing</a>.</p>

<p>My next site, well&hellip; may involve pigskin.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Measuring the Game Backlog, aka "the Pile of Shame"]]></title>
    <link href="http://brendonrapp.github.io/2008/02/03/measuring-the-game-backlog-aka-the-pile-of-shame/"/>
    <updated>2008-02-03T14:44:21-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://brendonrapp.github.io/2008/02/03/measuring-the-game-backlog-aka-the-pile-of-shame</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There are a great many games that I have intended to play (and finish), but have not yet done so. Some are games that I started but didn&rsquo;t follow through, and others are games I simply never got to. I&rsquo;ve done a great job lately in finishing games that I start, and I&rsquo;m now going back and playing games I&rsquo;ve missed (as evidenced by the Gearbox Half-Life expansions and now the Brothers in Arms titles). There&rsquo;s a good chance I will edit this post and add more games in as I think of them.</p>

<p><strong>Nintendo console games:</strong>
<em>Super NES:
</em>Yoshi&rsquo;s Island: Super Mario World 2
Super Metroid (was <em>this</em> close to finishing)
ActRaiser
Super Mario RPG</p>

<p><em>Nintendo 64:</em>
Super Mario 64 (played halfway many times, never finished)
Legend of Zelda: Ocarina of Time (played &frac34; the way twice, never finished)
Paper Mario</p>

<p><em>GameCube:</em>
Resident Evil 4 (GameCube controller aiming was awful, looking forward to playing Wii version)
Eternal Darkness</p>

<p><strong>Other console games:
</strong><em>Genesis:</em>
Shadowrun
Earthworm Jim
General Chaos
Toejam &amp; Earl
Phantasy Star series
Shining Force series
Herzog Zwei
Warsong</p>

<p><strong>PC RPGs:
</strong>Wasteland
Ultima series
Baldur&rsquo;s Gate series
Icewind Dale series
Planescape: Torment
Neverwinter Nights series
Dungeon Siege series
Titan Quest series
Anachronox
Elder Scrolls: Morrowind
The Witcher
Fable: The Lost Chapters</p>

<p><strong>PC Action/First Person games:</strong>
Thief series (played some of each, never completed)
System Shock
No One Lives Forever series
Brothers in Arms series
SWAT 4
Far Cry
Crysis</p>

<p><strong>PC Strategy:</strong>
X-COM: UFO Defense
Starflight
Star Control II
Supreme Commander
Company of Heroes (plus expansion)
Command &amp; Conquer series
Freedom Force series
WarCraft III
Tropico
Darwinia
Uplink</p>

<p><strong>PC Adventure Games (point-and-click)</strong>
<em>LucasArts:</em>
Zak McKraken and the Alien Mindbenders
Loom
The Dig
Indiana Jones and the Last Crusade
Indiana Jones and the Fate of Atlantis
Sam &amp; Max Hit the Road (never finished it)</p>

<p><em>Sierra:
</em>(all of them &ndash; yes, all)</p>

<p><em>Others:
</em>The Space Bar
Obsidian
The Last Express
The Longest Journey series
Syberia series
Broken Sword series
I Have No Mouth and I Must Scream
Myst
Zork: Grand Inquisitor</p>

<p>Whew! That&rsquo;s no small list. Let&rsquo;s just say that when the spring/summer game release drought hits, I won&rsquo;t be complaining about it. Probably not during 2009&rsquo;s summer either.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
