<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Sports | Economy of Effort]]></title>
  <link href="http://brendonrapp.github.io/categories/sports/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://brendonrapp.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-07-04T21:38:22-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://brendonrapp.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Brendon Rapp]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Strange and Amazing]]></title>
    <link href="http://brendonrapp.github.io/2011/04/15/strange-and-amazing/"/>
    <updated>2011-04-15T15:09:39-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://brendonrapp.github.io/2011/04/15/strange-and-amazing</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As a kid of around 9 or 10, I had a &ldquo;young adult&rdquo; focused football book. It was all about stories of players and games from football&rsquo;s past. It&rsquo;s almost the only football book I remember owning, and I literally read the covers off of it.</p>

<p>Having no idea who authored it or any sort of inkling of the book title, I tried to find the book. Armed only with a vague memory of what it looked like (yellowed pages, and some yellow on the cover somewhere) and a much less vague memory of the stories contained within, I headed over to Google Books to try and come up with some search queries to find the book in their archive of scanned books.</p>

<p>My first go-to queries related to the 222-0 Cumberland vs. Georgia Tech game. I knew very well that this story came from that book, but no joy. I searched for Dick &ldquo;Night Train&rdquo; Lane, but the hits there didn&rsquo;t yield my book either.</p>

<p>Finally, I struck gold. I remembered the story of Tony Dorsett and his 1,000 yard season streak (dating back to his high school days), and how the streak was broken by the 1982 player&rsquo;s strike. (In my memory, I thought it was the 1987 strike, but luckily, that didn&rsquo;t matter). I searched for: <a href="https://encrypted.google.com/search?q=tony+dorsett+strike&amp;btnG=Search&amp;hl=en&amp;tbo=1&amp;tbm=bks&amp;sa=2">Tony Dorsett 1,000 yards strike</a> and <a href="http://books.google.com/books?id=5nNt_sPPMOMC&amp;q=tony+dorsett+strike&amp;dq=tony+dorsett+strike&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=ZhGmTdnmOIH2tgOB3t35DA&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=4&amp;ved=0CDwQ6AEwAw">found the exact page I was looking for</a>:</p>

<p><a href="http://www.economyofeffort.com/wp-content/uploads/2011/04/dorsett.png"><img src="http://www.economyofeffort.com/wp-content/uploads/2011/04/dorsett.png" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>It was only a snippet, but I vividly remember the phrasing of those sentences. I knew I had found what I had been trying in vain for the past few years to dig up in my memory.</p>

<p>The book was Sports Illustrated: Strange and Amazing Football Stories, written in 1986. And I&rsquo;ve come to figure out that I was incredibly lucky with that search phrase. Google Books does not have anywhere near the full text of the book archived, which is why neither Cumberland nor Night Train put me on the right track. Now that I knew the book&rsquo;s name and could pull it up on Google Books, I had a search bar that searched only this specific book. Most of the stories I remembered came up with no hits, and even ones that did came up with no scanned page snippets. The only hit I&rsquo;ve been able to come up with that gave me a look at the book was the Dorsett query.</p>

<p>But that was of no consequence any longer. Now I knew the book&rsquo;s name and author. Mystery solved; I had the bastard right where I wanted him. Next stop was Amazon, which gave me plenty of used copies to choose from. I picked out one listed in good condition, and a few days later:</p>

<p><a href="http://www.economyofeffort.com/wp-content/uploads/2011/04/5614821296_f2c188c855_b.jpg"><img src="http://www.economyofeffort.com/wp-content/uploads/2011/04/5614821296_f2c188c855_b.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>Mission accomplished.</p>

<p>Not being very long, the book was easy to breeze through in an evening. Reading through it confirmed every memory I had about it, and how many old football stories and tales of old players I knew came directly from this book:</p>

<ul>
<li>Cumberland losing to Georgia Tech in the most lopsided game ever, 222-0</li>
<li>The New York Giants spanking Sammy Baugh&rsquo;s Redskins 73-0 in the 1940 championship game</li>
<li>The <em>Heidi</em> game</li>
<li>The Stanford band game</li>
<li>Flutie&rsquo;s hail mary</li>
<li>Old players like Bronko Nagurski, Red Grange, Dick &ldquo;Night Train&rdquo; Lane</li>
<li>Jim Thorpe and the Oorang Indians (and lots of tales of early pro teams, which were more like traveling acts than a sports league)</li>
<li>Raymond Berry and his practice habits (including making his wife, Sally Berry, throw him passes to get more reps)</li>
<li>Chuck Bednarik as the last bastion of iron man football</li>
<li>Knute Rockne&rsquo;s Notre Dame all-stars versus the New York Giants</li>
<li>Abner Haynes&rsquo;s &ldquo;we&rsquo;ll kick to the clock&rdquo;</li>
</ul>


<p>I could list plenty more. It&rsquo;s a nice collection of stories, especially given what the  book is. The author, Bill Gutman, apparently churned out these kinds of young reader sports books by the dozen, for publishers like Scholastic and, as in the case of this book, Archway (putting it alongside the likes of Hardy Boys and Nancy Drew books).</p>

<p>Sadly, fact-checking may have been a tad loose in this book, as I picked out one glaring factual error. At the end of telling the Jerry Kramer story, the author tied things up with a nice but oh-so-wrong sentence:</p>

<blockquote><p>&ldquo;No wonder Jerry Kramer ended up in pro football&rsquo;s Hall of Fame&rdquo;.</p></blockquote>

<p>Should I ever meet Kramer, I would ask him to sign this book, a relic from an alternate reality exactly like our own save for a Jerry Kramer bust in Canton.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[5 Things: Far Cry]]></title>
    <link href="http://brendonrapp.github.io/2009/04/07/5-things-far-cry/"/>
    <updated>2009-04-07T12:46:27-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://brendonrapp.github.io/2009/04/07/5-things-far-cry</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In honor of <a href="http://sportsillustrated.cnn.com/writers/peter_king/archive/">Peter King</a>&rsquo;s &ldquo;5 Things I Think I Think&rdquo; musing on the NFL, I present my own &ldquo;five things&rdquo; on games I have recently played.</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s kick things off with 5 Things I Think I Think about&hellip;</p>

<p><img src="http://www.techpowerup.com/reviews/EVGA/GeForce_8800_GS/images/farcry.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p><strong>1. I think I&rsquo;m in love with the &ldquo;sandbox&rdquo; approach to shooter battles.</strong> The game Far Cry was when I was funneled through hallways and tunnels is probably a game I would have played and enjoyed, even if at a C+, B- level or so. The game Far Cry was when I was allowed to sneak through brush, survey hostiles in the distance, plan a course of action, and execute it, is a game I <em>loved</em>.</p>

<p>For a game that wasn&rsquo;t strictly a stealth action title, I was surprised at how reasonable and &ldquo;fair&rdquo; the enemy&rsquo;s ability to detect the player was. There were very, very few instances of &ldquo;how the heck did he &lsquo;see&rsquo; me?&rdquo;. I always felt comfortable that, if there was enough brush in front of me to block them from my view, I would in turn be blocked from their view.</p>

<p>I really enjoyed the freedom of being able to approach situations from many different angles. I often eschewed taking vehicles and running through what was clearly a planned &ldquo;vehicle&rdquo; sequence, opting instead to creep through the vegetation. It was extremely satisfying to be able to exercise a little <em>creativity</em> in playing the game. So many games really force you to flip the &ldquo;off&rdquo; switch in your brain and just follow in-game cues. How many times have you been playing a game and asked yourself, &ldquo;what am I <em>supposed</em> to do?&rdquo;, instead of, &ldquo;how <em>can</em> I approach this?&rdquo;. As gamers, we&rsquo;ve become conditioned to try and seek the designed course of action. Years and years of &ldquo;locked&rdquo; doors and invisible walls have taught us to turn off the brain and follow the cues.</p>

<p>Given this newfound love for &ldquo;sandbox&rdquo; FPS battles, it seems like kismet that the FPS games at the top of my &ldquo;to-play&rdquo; list are the following: Crysis, Crysis: Warhead, S.T.A.L.K.E.R., S.T.A.L.K.E.R.: Clear Sky, and Far Cry 2.</p>

<p><img src="http://www.economyofeffort.com/wp-content/uploads/2009/04/trigen.jpg" alt="trigen" /></p>

<p><strong>2. I think the mutant menace was extremely overstated.</strong> I didn&rsquo;t play Far Cry back in 2004-05 (save for the demo), but like any forum-dwelling gamer, I&rsquo;m well aware of its reputation: &ldquo;a great game, until those damn <em>mutants</em> showed up&rdquo;. So when the mutants &ndash; Trigens &ndash; showed up in level 5 (of 20), I thought the jig might be up. I&rsquo;ve been disciplining myself to pull the plug on games before they outlive their ability to entertain me, as it&rsquo;s my nature to simply want to <em>finish</em> them anyway. So, from mission 5 onward, we were on orange alert. And a few early encounters almost led to premature deletion, as getting pounced by one of those bastards was essentially insta-death.</p>

<p>But just before it all fell apart, the tides turned. I got a semiautomatic combat shotgun, giving me a capable counter to the pouncing mutants in close encounters. Then the &ldquo;CryVision&rdquo; night vision/thermal goggles were acquired, allowing me to hunt <em>them</em> in the outdoor areas. The mutants didn&rsquo;t dominate the rest of the game, as new enemies are often so prone to do &ndash; just when a mutant-heavy sequence would become tiresome, the game would swing back to encounters against theÂ  reasonably clever human AI enemies. And most important, the tunneled indoor areas always gave way to more expansive outdoor segments, returning the game to its bread and butter.</p>

<p>I would have preferred the game sans-mutants, which makes Far Cry 2 appealing, even if it&rsquo;s quite a different game. But the mutants failed to live up to their game-destroying reputation.</p>

<p><strong>3. I think I like ridiculous, juvenile &ldquo;sexual content&rdquo; a little too much.</strong> Please don&rsquo;t misunderstand me. I know a pathetic appeal to teenage nerd sexual fantasy when I see it. Like the obnoxious fawning from the demon girl in Dark Messiah of Might and Magic. But here&rsquo;s the thing&hellip;</p>

<p><img src="http://www.economyofeffort.com/wp-content/uploads/2009/04/farcryval01.jpg" alt="farcryval01" /></p>

<p><img src="http://www.economyofeffort.com/wp-content/uploads/2009/04/farcryval02.jpg" alt="farcryval02" /></p>

<p>&hellip; I just don&rsquo;t care.</p>

<p>I love it. Exaggerated virtual girls with over-the-top, oversexed attitudes and bodies to match&hellip; I love it all. No matter how fake, or how transparent the manipulation, I&rsquo;ll happily wallow in a sea of horny video game girls.</p>

<p><strong>4. I think waiting a few years to play the game was a good idea (also: Steam sales are the best).</strong> When the game was new, playing Far Cry at 1680x1050 with everything cranked to Very High would&rsquo;ve been a pipe dream. But with a nice midrange 8800 GT, that&rsquo;s exactly how I played the game, with a framerate that was permanently well above 60 fps. So, so butter smooth. I&rsquo;m a stickler for framerate. Nothing looks better than a game that runs silky smooth. I have Far Cry 2, and I can get good framerates with decent detail settings right now, but I&rsquo;m not firing up the game again until I get my new video card.</p>

<p>I bought Far Cry a couple of weekends ago, during Ubisoft&rsquo;s week of Steam sales. The weekend sale was a 4-pack: Beyond Good and Evil, Far Cry, IL-2 Sturmovik, and Dark Messiah of Might and Magic, all for $9.99. I already owned BG&amp;E and IL-2, but I figured that would just make Far Cry and Dark Messiah $5 each. I definitely got my $5 out of Far Cry.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve never regretted a Steam sale purchase, but I continue to regret purchases I <em>didn&rsquo;t</em> make (WHY did I not buy Vampire: Bloodlines for $10 back in October??)</p>

<p><img src="http://www.economyofeffort.com/wp-content/uploads/2009/04/farcry01.jpg" alt="farcry01" /></p>

<p><strong>5. I think I&rsquo;m glad I played the game on Medium difficulty.</strong> Far Cry was not a forgiving game. I think one of the reasons I was able to live with the mutant presence was because I wasn&rsquo;t playing on one of the advanced difficulty levels. Playing on harder difficulty levels is something that I&rsquo;m trying to discipline myself into doing. Too often, I cheat myself out of a rewarding challenge by just going with the default difficulty setting. Although it is fun to just blast through a game with no frustration, I have found that, like a badly coached sports team, I &ldquo;play down&rdquo; to the competition. I just cruise through on autopilot, and eventually find certain parts hard because I&rsquo;m not <em>really</em> trying.</p>

<p>Far Cry was not one of those games. I have no doubt that I could have prevailed on higher difficulty settings, but with a lot more frustration. Certain scenes clearly exist to beat the player senseless and force him/her to re-play the section many times in order to &ldquo;get it right&rdquo;. I was certainly annoyed by a couple of them, and I have no doubt that dealing with them on a hard difficulty would&rsquo;ve put a real dent in my enjoyment of the game. For this title at least, chickening out was the right way to go.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Bookmark Alert: Must-Know Football Sites]]></title>
    <link href="http://brendonrapp.github.io/2007/07/26/bookmark-alert-must-know-football-sites/"/>
    <updated>2007-07-26T16:31:05-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://brendonrapp.github.io/2007/07/26/bookmark-alert-must-know-football-sites</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The following is a quick peek into my football related bookmarks&hellip;</p>

<p><a href="http://jaguars.com/News/AskVic.aspx">Ask Vic column</a> at Jaguars.com &ndash; It&rsquo;s rare to find candid commentary on an official team website, but Ask Vic is exactly that. The idea is brilliant: an old curmudgeon football guy writing an online column in a wired age far removed from his old-school roots. Although ostensibly a Jaguars Q&amp;A column, the focus of the articles tends to drift away from the Jaguars and spend a lot of time on general NFL topics. Common themes include the &lsquo;70s Steelers, running and stopping the run, intricacies of the salary cap era, building through the draft, Vic&rsquo;s disdain of newfangled things like video games and fantasy football, lots of old players that today&rsquo;s young fans have never heard of, quality of the hot dogs in various teams&rsquo; press booths, and many more. I don&rsquo;t doubt that Vic hams up the cranky old pigskin writer role a bit for effect, but there&rsquo;s an undeniable character there that makes it a favorite of NFL fans, not just Jaguar fans.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.profootballtalk.com/rumormill.htm">ProFootballTalk.com&rsquo;s Rumor Mill</a> &ndash; This has been a very interesting site to watch over the past few years. It has become a forum for leaked stories from league insiders, the kind of stuff that rarely ends up in an official press release. Although some stories end up being firmly the stuff of rumor, a lot of real stories end up breaking here <em>long</em> before the &ldquo;real media&rdquo; gets on them. The Vick dogfighting story, for example, was tracked there for weeks before anyone else started even whispering about it. The real value, though, are the NFL insider rumblings that never turn into substantiated reports. Despite the &ldquo;dirty laundry&rdquo; type of content that is often a staple of the blog, the site manages to maintain a light tone thanks to a self-deprecating quality. The reports aren&rsquo;t always correct, but they&rsquo;re right more often than they should be, and they&rsquo;re always a good read either way.</p>

<p><a href="http://ffmastermind.com/quickbits.php">FFMastermind&rsquo;s NFL Quick Bits</a> &ndash; FFMastermind has been around since 1996, and frankly the site looks almost the same <a href="http://web.archive.org/web/19981205090957/www.ffmastermind.com/bits/hot.shtml">as it did back then</a>. FFMastermind.com offers a lot of premium fantasy football content, but the wonderful NFL Quick Bits page is free and has been a staple of my bookmarks for over a decade now. Despite the complete lack of technical progress (it&rsquo;s just a big fat heap of static content, no RSS feed to be found), it&rsquo;s still the best collection of one-stop NFL news around. All of the stories that appear in a team&rsquo;s local press clippings end up collected on this page. It makes it easy to keep up on the kind of news that local beat writers dig up, without having to actually follow 32 different local newspapers' sports sections. Did you know who Marques Colston was <em>before</em> last season started, and were you aware he was the team&rsquo;s starting WR2? I was, and it was thanks to the reports that local Saints writers wrote, which ended up being quoted on NFL Quick Bits.</p>

<p><a href="http://footballoutsiders.com/">Football Outsiders</a> is really a gem. In an Internet era of everyone echoing everyone else&rsquo;s content and calling it &ldquo;news&rdquo;, it&rsquo;s rare to see a site doing the kind of unique, original content that Football Outsiders does. From their &ldquo;Play of the Day&rdquo; breakdown of specific NFL plays (the kind of actual X&rsquo;s and O&rsquo;s breakdown that is nearly impossible to find online), to their <em>deep</em> statistical analyses (some of which may be of questionable value, but all of which are highly interesting), to some slightly more traditional NFL and fantasy football breakdowns, Football Outsiders is just brilliant. It&rsquo;s the kind of in-depth football content that nobody else is out there providing. These guys also put out the annual Pro Football Prospectus publication, which I ordered for the first time this year. I can&rsquo;t wait to get my hands on it.</p>

<p><a href="http://sportsillustrated.cnn.com/writers/dr_z/archive/index.html">Dr. Z&rsquo;s NFL Mailbag</a> &ndash;  A lot of NFL writers are total hacks. Paul Zimmerman, however, is one of the truly knowledgeable ones. His NFL Mailbag is somewhat similar to Ask Vic, if a bit overly wordy. Pretty much all of Dr. Z&rsquo;s columns take 3 pages to say what should fit into 1, but the content that is there is usually worth the digging.</p>

<p><a href="http://nfl.com/writers/kirwan">Pat Kirwan at NFL.com</a> &ndash; Another NFL writer worth reading. Kirwan is excellent on SIRIUS NFL Radio,  and he&rsquo;s great on NFL.com as well. His coaching &amp; front office background shines through in his league knowledge, and he provides a nice perspective on current situations that goes above just re-telling the daily league news.</p>

<p><a href="http://sportsillustrated.cnn.com/writers/peter_king/archive/index.html">Peter King&rsquo;s Monday Morning Quarterback</a> &ndash; This column doesn&rsquo;t get archived into its own page, so the link goes to King&rsquo;s entire SI.com archive. Thankfully, King has some good stories outside of MMQ, but be sure to check out MMQ every Monday.</p>

<p><a href="http://sports.espn.go.com/keyword/search?searchString=Gregg_Easterbrook">Gregg Easterbrook&rsquo;s Tuesday Morning Quarterback</a> &ndash; ESPN.com fares no better than SI.com in organizing content, so here too is a link to an archive of all Gregg Easterbrook writings at ESPN.com. It works out better here, though, as TMQ is basically all Easterbrook does. :) TMQ is a more humorous take on the week in football, sneaking in a bit of insight wrapped in all that irreverent chatter.</p>

<p>No direct link for this one since it&rsquo;s part of a premium service, but the training camp reports at <a href="http://www.footballinjuries.com">FootballInjuries.com</a> are my top source of information during July and August.  They are wonderful, &ldquo;boots on the ground&rdquo; detailed reports of what is going on at all 32 NFL training camps. During the season, the service is also the best source of injury information, letting you know exactly how much a particular player participated (or didn&rsquo;t participate) in each practice session of the week. A great deal of the site&rsquo;s content is fantasy related, and although I&rsquo;m not a big fan of their player rankings (partner site <a href="http://www.fantasyguru.com">FantasyGuru.com</a> is much better in this regard, IMO), I do find great value in their ADP (Average Draft Position) reports, incorporating that information into my personal fantasy draft sheets.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.nfldraftcountdown.com/">NFL Draft Countdown</a> &ndash;  From February through April, this is the place to be. Best draft info you can get without paying out the nose for a premium service.</p>

<p>Finally, this site isn&rsquo;t for reading, but <a href="http://www.pro-football-reference.com/">pro-football-reference.com</a> is an excellent one-stop source of stats, standings, Pro Bowl rosters, etc, going as far back as 1920. Defensive stats, sadly, only go back to 2002, which may be a function of the puzzling approach the NFL takes toward defensive stats (sacks weren&rsquo;t an official stat until 1982, and tackles are still not an official stat). Outside of that, this is a fantastic reference site, and something I constantly refer to.</p>

<p>Anything I missed?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Forward Progress Radio]]></title>
    <link href="http://brendonrapp.github.io/2006/04/16/forward-progress-radio/"/>
    <updated>2006-04-16T17:40:36-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://brendonrapp.github.io/2006/04/16/forward-progress-radio</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://static.flickr.com/44/115212393_dab79c9ba8.jpg" alt="forward progress logo v1.0" />  I haven&rsquo;t posted in a long time, but there&rsquo;s a reason why &ndash; I&rsquo;ve been hard at work on a nice little project.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve created the football podcast that I&rsquo;ve been wanting someone else to create: <a href="http://www.forwardprogressradio.com">Forward Progress Radio</a>.</p>

<p>Forward Progress Radio is a weekly podcast of NFL news and analysis. Each show will be about 20 minutes long, though these first few are more like 40 minutes because of the amount of stuff there is to cover before the draft.</p>

<p>If you&rsquo;re a football fan, please check the &lsquo;cast out. It should be showing up in the iTunes directory shortly, if it&rsquo;s not already there.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[More Sports]]></title>
    <link href="http://brendonrapp.github.io/2005/11/15/more-sports/"/>
    <updated>2005-11-15T15:48:54-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://brendonrapp.github.io/2005/11/15/more-sports</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://jaguars.com/story/Images/240x135/Story(4736" alt="" />240x135.jpg) As if the sports weekend wasn&rsquo;t good enough after Fresno State&rsquo;s victory over Boise, the Jacksonville Jaguars put a beatdown on the Baltimore Ravens on Sunday, 30-3. It&rsquo;s about time that Greg Jones started carrying the rock like the power back he was expected to be. It&rsquo;s about time Matt Jones started being a threat to opposing defenders. It&rsquo;s about time the offensive line (bolstered by rookie Khalif Barnes) kept defenders off of Byron Leftwich&rsquo;s back. And it&rsquo;s about time the Jaguars dominated a weaker opponent, instead of playing down to the competition.</p>

<p>Plus, in fantasy football, I won. And two of the three teams that I&rsquo;m fighting against for wildcard spots lost. AND, the team ahead of me in my division lost, putting me right back into the divisional race &ndash; so I might not even need a wildcard spot.</p>

<p>And the Kings keep on winning. They&rsquo;re clearly the cream of the Pacific Division right now.</p>

<p>Now, here&rsquo;s hoping NEXT weekend is just as sweet. If Fresno can knock off USC, then it wouldn&rsquo;t matter what happened the rest of the weekend&hellip;</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
