<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Life | Economy of Effort]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.economyofeffort.com/categories/life/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.economyofeffort.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-08-11T21:09:01-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.economyofeffort.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Brendon Rapp]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Catching Up]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.economyofeffort.com/2006/06/07/catching-up/"/>
    <updated>2006-06-07T16:47:32-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.economyofeffort.com/2006/06/07/catching-up</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A couple of weeks ago, I saw one of my best friends for the first time in years. Ryan had been in the navy and all over the world, and it&rsquo;s nice to have him back around. We spent a lot of time hanging out in high school. We used to play old PC games with a couple of crappy machines and a null modem cable, thrashing each other in WarCraft (the original, Orcs and Humans, and just a demo version at that) and a pathetic shooter most of you have never heard of &ndash; <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Corridor_7">Corridor 7</a>, from the people that would go on to develop the unforgettably bad BUILD-engine based William Shatner&rsquo;s <a href="http://www.mobygames.com/game/dos/william-shatners-tekwar/reviews/reviewerId,5107/">TekWar</a>. Corridor 7 was terrible, but it had multiplayer that functioned, which was good enough for us at the time. It was great talking to Ryan after so long. He agreed to be in the wedding party, despite reservations about having to wear a tux.</p>

<p><img src="http://static.flickr.com/47/162861196_9758c30083_m.jpg" alt="" /> This Sunday sees the US release of the Nintendo DS Lite, and I will be getting one. Stacey will too. I&rsquo;m actually selling my PSP to help fund it, though I have every intention on buying another PSP later in the future (it&rsquo;s Sony&rsquo;s worst-kept secret that a PSP revision is planned for the future, with a large additional internal memory as a likely feature addition). I can live without the PSP (and/or borrow Logan&rsquo;s from time to time) in the meanwhile. I am very interested in <a href="http://psp.ign.com/articles/709/709489p1.html">Field Commander</a>, <a href="http://www.eurogamer.net/article.php?article_id=65319">LocoRoco</a>, and Killzone: Liberation. Maybe we&rsquo;ll rent those for the trip to Texas at the end of this month.</p>

<p>In other news, I dumped Gentoo Linux (actually, I just tar&rsquo;d and bzip&rsquo;d my root directory up and stored it on my file server) and installed Ubuntu Linux. Ubuntu (and the Kubuntu desktop) has gotten very nice. I always end up back with Gentoo, but this one might <em>finally</em> be the binary distro that lets me live without wanting to go back to a tedious but flexible source-based distro. I especially love the now-very-workable NetworkManager (and KNetworkManager) utility, which is absent in Gentoo.</p>

<p><img src="http://static.flickr.com/54/162867493_4fa9479285_m.jpg" alt="" /> Lastly, my <a href="http://static.flickr.com/54/162867493_4fa9479285_o.jpg">wife-to-be and I</a> have been doing our wedding registries. A lot of stuff falls under the category of &ldquo;don&rsquo;t care&rdquo; for me, so she&rsquo;s had free reign over a lot of that (like, say, dish towels &ndash; just not my area of interest). I have won a few key skirmishes in the war of contested items, though. I got my silverware of choice, and I think we have finally agreed on my choice of bedding. Most stuff, however, is all her, and that&rsquo;s fine. I&rsquo;m certain she&rsquo;ll make our home look beautiful and have it well-stocked with everything we need. I&rsquo;ve even come around to her choice of <a href="http://www.target.com/gp/detail.html/601-9080267-9332126?%5Fencoding=UTF8&amp;coliid=I2YJN8HKEHGNMB&amp;asin=B000EJ0CD2&amp;colid=2QY7O2JBND0FB&amp;bckreg=cw">dinnerware</a>, which reminds me of &ldquo;light speed&rdquo; in the original Star Wars movies.</p>

<p>All is well. I hope to really get deep into writing code over the next couple of weeks. I&rsquo;ve said that I&rsquo;m going to do it, but so far it hasn&rsquo;t quite happened. Starting is the hardest part &ndash; once I&rsquo;m in, I&rsquo;ll stay coding until I drop.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Engaged]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.economyofeffort.com/2006/03/07/engaged/"/>
    <updated>2006-03-07T12:12:22-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.economyofeffort.com/2006/03/07/engaged</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>One week before we had been dating for exactly four years, I asked Stacey to marry me. But not quite so simply.</p>

<p>No, first, she had to run all over town in a &ldquo;scavenger hunt&rdquo; patterned after The Amazing Race, complete with Logan serving as cameraman with his fine Sony HD camcorder.</p>

<p>At each stop of the &ldquo;race&rdquo;, she would find a relative or friend. Three of her friends came from out of town to participate. She had to do various tasks like find a certain item inside a store, paint a picture, race a go-kart, and (my favorite) participate in a miniature NFL combine, complete with 40-yard-dash time and Wonderlic test. Perhaps the best moment is when she didn&rsquo;t know what the word &ldquo;gridiron&rdquo; referred to, and she ended up asking people in the mall what it meant &ndash; finally getting an answer from former Oakland Raider and AFL Hall of Fame receiver Art Powell, who was signing autographs in the mall.</p>

<p>At the end, she found everyone waiting for her at the restaurant at which we had our first date. There, I proposed to her, she accepted (this was a foregone conclusion &ndash; she had been pretty much bugging me to hurry up the proposal for some time ), and we all enjoyed a wonderful Japanese food dinner.</p>

<p>Soon, we will shoot some B-roll, and take all of that film and cut it together into a TV-style broadcast, complete with dramatic soundtrack and all that fun stuff. We&rsquo;ll master it to a DVD, and keep it forever.</p>

<p>Stacey has a <a href="http://queenstacey-25.livejournal.com/60784.html">more complete account</a> of the events on her journal. I don&rsquo;t have the energy to try and describe it as she did, and I was at &ldquo;mission control&rdquo; the whole time anyway. Needless to say, organizing and executing this plan was a LOT of work and planning, and the logistics were my biggest stressing point.</p>

<p>Stacey has also created a <a href="http://staceyandbrendon.weddingannouncer.com/">website at weddingannouncer.com</a> where information of our wedding-to-be will be posted. She&rsquo;s got some stuff up now.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Lord Stanley, Python, and Peter Jackson]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.economyofeffort.com/2006/01/26/lord-stanley-python-and-peter-jackson/"/>
    <updated>2006-01-26T08:43:51-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.economyofeffort.com/2006/01/26/lord-stanley-python-and-peter-jackson</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://static.flickr.com/23/91579660_7ca7160f65_m.jpg" alt="" /> Last night, I touched Lord Stanley&rsquo;s Cup. The ECHL All-Star Game was hosted here in Fresno, at the wonderful Save Mart Center. Along for the ride was the Stanley Cup as well as the ECHL&rsquo;s own prize, the Kelly Cup. Stacey and I had our pictures taken with the Cup. The game was also fun, more for the company (Kate and Kristyn) than the game itself.</p>

<p>I have started experimenting with Python and the pygame library, in order to create a quick puzzle game. I need to build up a portfolio of demos, and so I am going to learn some new languages and libraries along the way. I&rsquo;d be so comfortable just jumping into C++ and OpenGL to do everything, but when it comes to skill sets, Wider Is Better.</p>

<p><img src="http://static.flickr.com/11/91579661_655e379883_m.jpg" alt="" /> GameFly sent me the next game I had in my queue: Peter Jackson&rsquo;s King Kong for the Xbox 360. I&rsquo;ve played it for about half an hour. Very pretty game, seems like a well-executed concept too. One complaint: playing it on my VGA monitor in 1280x1024, the picture appears as if it is rendered in 16:9 but then letterboxed on top of that too. The viewing size is VERY short. I&rsquo;ve noticed a few graphical gotchas in playing the 360 on a VGA display, rather than an SDTV or an HDTV. I appreciate it when games are letterboxed, but I think there&rsquo;s something funky going on in this case. No matter &ndash; I&rsquo;ll still play through anything Michel Ansel (Beyond Good and Evil) creates from here on out.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Standoff at the Japanese Take-Out Place]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.economyofeffort.com/2005/12/22/standoff-at-the-japanese-take-out-place/"/>
    <updated>2005-12-22T15:12:15-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.economyofeffort.com/2005/12/22/standoff-at-the-japanese-take-out-place</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A few days ago, I witnessed one of those interesting sequences of events that seem completely puzzling due to the fact that you came into the sequence halfway. Here&rsquo;s what happened:</p>

<p>As I walked into this Japanese food take-out place, I stood in a short line, waiting to place my order. A man walked from the seating area of the place towards the counter. As he got close, the two girls behind the counter that he walked towards waved their hands at him in a way that you do to tell a person, &ldquo;no, you misunderstand, you don&rsquo;t have to do that&rdquo;&hellip; not in a panicked or fearful sense, but just in a customer service sense. He got to the counter, and he slammed down his receipt and a single dime. He looked at them, and said in a slow, drawn-out firm tone: &ldquo;I will never come in here again.&rdquo; The girls looked stunned as he turned around and walked back to his seat. I overheard him mutter to someone something about how &ldquo;she screwed up&rdquo;, and he took his seat and began eating again.</p>

<p>That&rsquo;s it, and I have not been able to mentally construct a sequence of events that lead up to that exchange. The dime is an interesting clue. Were they harassing him over ten cents? It sure didn&rsquo;t seem like they cared about the dime. Perhaps it&rsquo;s a red herring, and it was just some change he had in his hand and he dropped it as he slammed down the receipt. I would guess that perhaps he was given the wrong order, but he sat back down afterwards and chowed down his food.</p>

<p>Some people have very short fuses when it comes to the people that serve them food. I know Stacey has a bit of a short fuse, a lot shorter than is comfortable for me. But nothing that would end in something like this. Maybe this guy just had a REALLY short fuse about any error in his order or service.</p>

<p>I don&rsquo;t know. I have no clue really. It&rsquo;s one of those things that might not be very interesting if given all the details, but in lieu of that, it&rsquo;s quite puzzling.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What a week]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.economyofeffort.com/2005/10/26/what-a-week/"/>
    <updated>2005-10-26T14:51:46-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.economyofeffort.com/2005/10/26/what-a-week</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I am typing this from downtown Austin, TX. But we&rsquo;ll get to that part later.</p>

<p>Last week, the gaming gods saw fit to bestow SOCOM III unto us. And it is good. Probably one of the last three PS2 games I will really play (the others being Shadow of the Colossus and, if Play Magazine is to be believed, Dragon Quest 8). The game has lived up to my expectations. Granted, I got a sneak peek with the online beta, but that was only one map. The rest of the game is of even higher quality than what we saw in the beta. When it comes to my online shooter time, I&rsquo;m left saying, &ldquo;Halo who?&rdquo; (No, Kristyn, this does not mean you will be able to defeat me.)</p>

<p>Also, I had a brutal midterm and an assignment to complete for a couple of my classes. I spent the first part of the week doing nothing but studying and taking occasional SOCOM breaks. When Friday came, I was happy. All I had to do was go to work, and after that, I was free &ndash; with a hockey game to go to that evening.</p>

<p>Then, as I sat in idle traffic on Nees Ave., some idiot girl rammed into our lane of traffic, causing the person behind me to hit into me and damage the whole back end of my car. This set of a flurry of insurance activity (given the fact that there are four participants and 3 insurance companies involved and all) that continues still. My back was sore for two days, but some rest and hockey-induced adrenaline chased that away.</p>

<p>So with all that behind me, I left Fresno today (well, Wednesday) for Austin to attend the <a href="http://www.gameconference.com">Austin Game Developer&rsquo;s Conference</a>. On my flight, I overheard some other attendees-to-be. Indeed, there seem to be many staying here in this Radisson Hotel, three blocks from the Convention Center where the conference is being held. My goal, of course, is to offer myself up to the recruiters, seeing as I am finishing school after next semester. Although this may end up being more of a dress rehearsal for next March&rsquo;s conference in San Jose, where I will have some demo work to present (instead of just a resume), it will still prove to be a valuable learning and preparatory experience. Plus, it will give me material to pull from for my research writing class. Anything on top of all of that is a great bonus.</p>

<p>My flight from Fresno to Dallas was long, but my PSP made the time pass quickly. On Tuesday, Grand Theft Auto: Liberty City Stories released for the PSP. I ran out and got the last copy that GameStop had, in preparation for my flight. It was a good move, as the game is excellent. It&rsquo;s basically GTA3 on the PSP. Some new content and tweaks that have occured in the series since then are present, of course. I was always more keen on Liberty City as a GTA setting than any of the others, so I&rsquo;m pleased with the return there in this game. The only danger now is that I might go out of my way to play it in situations where I wouldn&rsquo;t otherwise play my handheld games, and I&rsquo;ll run out of it before the next trip I take.</p>

<p>Anyway, I&rsquo;ll be posting a bunch of pictures and notes from the conference here. Thank goodness for free WiFi Internet access in the lobby.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
