<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: keyboards | Economy of Effort]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.economyofeffort.com/categories/keyboards/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.economyofeffort.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-12-16T20:35:46-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.economyofeffort.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Brendon Rapp]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Beyond Ctrl: Make That Caps Lock Key Useful]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.economyofeffort.com/2014/08/11/beyond-ctrl-remap-make-that-caps-lock-key-useful/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-11T14:19:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.economyofeffort.com/2014/08/11/beyond-ctrl-remap-make-that-caps-lock-key-useful</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>tl;dr: Supercharge your Caps Lock key by making it Esc when tapped, and Ctrl when held</strong></p>

<p>Caps Lock. A useless key sitting in prime keyboard real estate. Many software developers and power users repurpose the key by remapping it to Control.</p>

<p>After all, on old UNIX terminals, that&rsquo;s exactly what the key to the left of &ldquo;A&rdquo; was:</p>

<p><img src="/media/images/sun-keyboard.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>Replacing the Caps Lock key with Ctrl makes a lot of keyboard shortcuts more convenient. But we need not stop there. Some true Men and Women of Genius came to the realization that, since Ctrl&rsquo;s behavior is based around behind held down (a modifier key) and doesn&rsquo;t do anything when pressed and released, it is possible to make Caps Lock do something <em>else</em> when tapped instead of held. For Vim users, the obvious choice is the Esc key.</p>

<p>We can do this in both Mac OS X and Linux.</p>

<h2>OS X</h2>

<h3>If you want all Ctrl keys to behave like Esc when tapped</h3>

<p>This is the easiest way, and the option I use. (I rarely find myself hitting the normal Ctrl keys anyway.)</p>

<p>First, open System Preferences &ndash;> Keyboard, and click Modifier Keys button. Click the Caps Lock drop-down and set it to Control:</p>

<p><img src="/media/images/osx-remap-esc-key.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>Now, install <a href="https://pqrs.org/osx/karabiner/">Karabiner</a> (formerly known as KeyRemap4MacBook). If you are a Homebrew user, you should check out <a href="https://github.com/caskroom/homebrew-cask">Homebrew Cask</a> and install Karabiner with <code>$ brew cask install karabiner</code></p>

<p>Open Karabiner. Enable the first setting from the screenshot below:</p>

<p><img src="/media/images/karabiner-1.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>The other option I have there, &ldquo;Disable Escape Key&rdquo;, is something I&rsquo;ve done just to get myself in the habit of using the Caps Lock key for Esc. It is not required, it is just an option if you want to help train yourself to use the new key.</p>

<h3>If you only want the Caps Lock key to behave like Esc when tapped</h3>

<p>To do this, we&rsquo;re going to take a slightly different approach. Instead of using OS X&rsquo;s native Caps Lock remapping, we need to use another app, called <a href="https://pqrs.org/osx/karabiner/seil.html">Seil</a> (from the same developer as Karabiner) to remap the Esc key to F19, and then use Karabiner to map F19 to our cool Ctrl/Esc hybrid key.</p>

<p>Install both <a href="https://pqrs.org/osx/karabiner/">Karabiner</a> and <a href="https://pqrs.org/osx/karabiner/seil.html">Seil</a>. (Here again, if you use <a href="https://github.com/caskroom/homebrew-cask">Homebrew Cask</a>, you can do this with <code>$ brew cask install karabiner</code> and <code>$ brew cask install seil</code>)</p>

<p>Open Seil. First, enable the &ldquo;Change Caps Lock&rdquo; option, and set the keycode to 80:</p>

<p><img src="/media/images/seil.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>Next, in Karabiner, enable the &ldquo;F19 for Escape and Control&rdquo; option:</p>

<p><img src="/media/images/karabiner-2.png" alt="" /></p>

<h2>Linux</h2>

<p>To accomplish the same setup in Linux, we need to use a tool called <a href="https://github.com/alols/xcape">xcape</a>.</p>

<p>Build and install xcape per the instructions on the project&rsquo;s Wiki page. One additional step I take after building the app is copying the <code>xcape</code> executable to /usr/local/bin.</p>

<h3>If you only want the Caps Lock key to behave like Esc when tapped</h3>

<p>Add the following lines to your ~/.profile:
<code>
setxkbmap -option 'caps:ctrl_modifier'
xcape -e 'Caps_Lock=Escape'
</code></p>

<h3>If you want all Ctrl keys to behave like Esc when tapped</h3>

<p>Same as above, except we add more arguments to the xcape line:</p>

<p><code>
setxkbmap -option 'caps:ctrl_modifier'
xcape -e 'Caps_Lock=Escape;Control_L=Escape;Control_R=Escape'
</code></p>

<p>Note: If you use some other method of remapping the Caps Lock key to Ctrl (some desktop environments have it as an option in their Keyboard settings, much like OS X), then the Caps_Lock=Escape mapping may not do anything, and you will need to use the Control_L one.</p>

<p>One last little tidbit: Ubuntu 14.10 (&ldquo;Utopic&rdquo;) has xcape <a href="http://packages.ubuntu.com/utopic/xcape">in the universe repos</a>, at least as of the time of this writing. Hopefully it will be included in Ubuntu releases from here on out.</p>

<h2>Now Your Caps Lock Key Rules</h2>

<p>The most useless key on the keyboard (except maybe for Pause, when&rsquo;s the last time you used that?) is now your Swiss Army knife. Vim&rsquo;s keybindings will make a lot more sense now that you can use your pinky the way Bill Joy did on his old ADM3A terminal:</p>

<p><img src="/media/images/adm3a.png" alt="" /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[No Numpads]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.economyofeffort.com/2013/07/26/no-numpads/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-26T19:20:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.economyofeffort.com/2013/07/26/no-numpads</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>My mother is an accountant. Walk by her office on any given day, and you&rsquo;ll likely hear the mechanical sounds of an accounting calculator printing its results to a stream of paper.</p>

<p>{% img center /wp-content/uploads/2010/12/calculator.jpg 350 263 %}</p>

<p>I used to make fun of the endless <em>crunch-crunch-crunch</em> sound that echoed down the hallways.  These days, she tells me, the ol' hand calculator doesn&rsquo;t get quite as much use as before. More and more of the accounting business is computerized.</p>

<p>It comes as little surprise. Computers were invented to crunch numbers. When computers became machines that fit on a desktop, the &ldquo;killer apps&rdquo; were all about numbers: the first two applications named in Wikipedia&rsquo;s <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Killer_application">entry for killer applications</a> are Visicalc and Lotus 1-2-3.</p>

<p>Accordingly, it did not take long for personal computer manufacturers to take inspiration from those hand calculators and add the number pad to the right of the typewriter key layout.</p>

<p>{% img center /wp-content/uploads/2010/12/Terminal-dec-vt100.jpg 499 391 %} Personal computers, however, have moved well beyond the domain of the office desktop. Indeed, for most people, the computer is no longer thought of as a device for performing calculations. They are used for communication, and for accessing and storing data. I don&rsquo;t have data to back it up, but I would wager that most computer users don&rsquo;t punch in long sequences of numbers regularly.</p>

<p>And yet, while the computer has evolved, the number pad remains. Like the wings of a flightless bird. the vestigal number pad sits unused, eating up space on millions of desktops.</p>

<p>Oh sure, you use the number pad, you say. And perhaps you do. But do you really use it enough to dedicate 6 inches of desk width for it? More to the point, does <em>every</em> computer user? People are <a href="http://news.cnet.com/8301-31021_3-20005908-260.html">buying laptops and netbooks</a> for their computing devices more and more, and I don&rsquo;t ever hear people complaining about how much they miss the numpad.</p>

<p>And yet, the vast majority of keyboards for sale include the numpad. Finding keyboards without them takes some effort.</p>

<p>One of the few I became aware of when starting the search was the Happy Hacking Keyboard Lite.</p>

<p>{% img center /wp-content/uploads/2011/02/hhkb-lite.jpg %}</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s a nice, small deck. It uses a &ldquo;UNIX&rdquo; keyboard layout, like the ones on the old Sun boxes in one of the computer labs back at university.</p>

<p>Apple has come around on the idea of ditching the numpad. New iMacs come with a wireless keyboard that has no numpad.</p>

<p>{% img center /media/images/imac.jpg %}</p>

<p>I considered picking up one of these. And I actually did pick up a couple of Apple&rsquo;s discontinued wired USB tenkeyless keyboards.</p>

<p>{% img center /media/images/apple-compact-keyboard.jpg %}</p>

<p>They&rsquo;re not bad as spare keyboards to have around, but they were not going to be my primary keyboard. (My wife is using one on her desktop machine, though).</p>

<p>One keyboard I really want is the 84-key &ldquo;Space Saving&rdquo; version of the IBM Model M.</p>

<p>{% img center /wp-content/uploads/2010/12/spacesaver1280-300x203.jpg %} Sadly, they are awfully hard to come by. I watch for them on <a href="http://www.clickykeyboards.com">clickykeyboards.com</a> but it&rsquo;s just an endless list of <span style="color: #ff0000;"><strong>SOLD</strong></span> boards.</p>

<p>But the keyboard that ended my search was the <a href="http://elitekeyboards.com/products.php?sub=leopold,tenkeyless&amp;pid=fc200rtab">Leopold Tenkeyless Tactile Touch</a> from EliteKeyboards. It combined my desire for a compact no-numpad keyboard with the desire to have a mechanical keyboard.</p>

<p>{% img center /media/images/leopold.jpg %}</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s been a couple of years now since I bought this keyboard, and while the idea of spending $100 on a keyboard was a tough pill to swallow at the time, I would not hesitate to do it again. The compact size make life nicer on my desk, and the action of the mechanical key switches is so much more enjoyable than mashing the rubber dome switches on a non-mechanical keyboard.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
